除了我們生活的這個層次  還有其他的
We live on one level of existence, but there are others.
到處充滿了隱藏著的其他維度
These hidden dimensions of reality are everywhere.
從許多光年以外
Far away, across the light years.
到我們的腳下
Beneath our feet.
甚至在我們的體內
And even inside you and me.
我們由原子組成
We are made of atoms.
我們眼睛中的原子數量
There are more atoms in your eye,
比已知宇宙中所有星系的星星數量還多
than there are stars and all the galaxies of the known universe
上述情況也適用於任何
The same is true of any solid object
比你的指尖稍大的實體
larger than the tip of your little finger.
我由30萬億億億複雜排列的原子組成
I'm a collection of three billion, billion, billion
我是名叫尼爾·德葛拉司·泰森的原子組合體
intricately arranged atoms called Neil Degrasse Tyson.
你們也是一樣  只是名字不同
You are a similar collection with a different name.
我們通常不會這麼認為
We don't usually think of ourselves this way
因為這個級別的存在超過了我們感官的範疇
because that level of reality lies beyond the realm of our senses.
但是我們不會就此停止
But we're not gonna let that stop us.
我們還要繼續探究
We can go deeper into the wonder.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索 第六集
原子使所有事情變得有生氣
Atoms let matter do funny things.
要瞭解水 你需要知道它的原子規律
To understand water, you need to know what its atoms are doing.
每個水分子都是由
Every molecule of water is composed
兩個小小的氫原子
of two tiny hydrogen atoms
附著在一個大的氧原子上組成
attached to a larger oxygen atom.
因此我們稱之為 一氧化二氫
That's why we call it H20.
如果溫度不冷不熱
If it's not too hot or too cold,
分子們可以相互翻滾穿行
the molecules can slide and tumble past each other.
分子間還是有一些的粘滯性
There's still some stickiness between the molecules,
但是不足以讓它們變的緊密
but not enough to lock them into a rigid solid.
這就是液體的特性
That's what makes something a liquid.
太陽將水加熱
The sun warms the water.
給它更多的能量
And with more energy,
分子們移動加快
the molecules move faster.
溫度就是這樣的
That's all that temperature is.
當分子運到快到足以
Those molecules are moving fast enough
打破彼此間脆弱的聯繫時
to break the weak bonds that hold them to their neighbors.
就是蒸發
That's evaporation.
我們呼吸的空氣
The air we breathe is made of
就是由氮和氧的分子組成
nitrogen and oxygen molecules
再加一些水蒸氣和二氧化碳
with a scattering of water vapor and carbon dioxide.
小心
Incoming!
那是冷凝
That's condensation.
露珠就是冷凝戰勝蒸發的勝利果實
A dewdrop is the momentary triumph of condensation over evaporation.
這種現象持續下去
And while it lasts,
它就是一個小宇宙 包含它自己的世界
it's a little cosmos with its own worlds...
生物 戲劇性的事情
creatures, drama.
為了探索這滴露珠的廣闊領域
To explore the far-flung realms of this dewdrop
我們需要一艘船
we're gonna need a ship.
配上兩種引擎
One with twin engines...
科學和想像力
science and imagination.
那是單細胞的草履蟲
That's a single-celled paramecium,
它是在露珠中遊蕩中眾多嫻熟的獵人之一
one of a multitude of skilled hunter-warriors that roam the dewdrop.
但是它們同時也是獵物
But they, too, are hunted.
長頸蟲  草履蟲的死敵
The Dileptus. The paramecium's mortal enemy.
草履蟲或許可以幸運的直接擊殺
The paramecium might get lucky and score a direct hit.
就算不能
Even if it doesn't,
齊射攻擊造成的後座力拉開了
the recoil from the barrage will put some distance
草履蟲與攻擊者之間的距離
between the paramecium and its attacker.
我還能說些什麼呢
What can I say?
那就是露珠內的生活
That's life in the dewdrop.
那個小傢伙是水熊蟲
That little guy is tardigrade,
一種比針尖還小的動物
an animal smaller than the head of a pin.
可別小看它
Don't underestimate them.
水熊蟲在這個星球上的歷史比我們的還長久
Tardigrades have been living on this planet a lot longer than we have.
他們已存在地球上大約5億年
About 500 million years.
和我們的數量比例
For every one of us,
至少是1比10億
there's at least a billion of them.
它們可以在地球上任何地方生存
They can make a living anywhere on earth.
在最高的寒冷的山峰頂端
In the frigid peaks of the tallest mountains,
在噴發的火山口裏
in the cauldrons of erupting volcanoes,
在大洋的底部
and in the deep ocean vents at the bottom of the sea.
水熊蟲是如此的堅強
Tardigrades are so tough,
它們可以在真空中生存
they can survive naked in the vacuum of space.
它們經歷了最近五次的大滅絕
They've survived all five of the most recent mass extinctions on this planet.
如果外星人認為地球是水熊蟲的世界
A visitor from another world could be forgiven
那是絕對可以原諒的
for thinking of earth as the planet of the tardigrades.
如果還要看這滴露珠的其他地方 最好繼續往前走
If we're ever gonna get to the bottom of this dewdrop better get a move on.
每片葉子和苔蘚
Every leaf and tiny clump of moss
都有成千上萬的
has hundreds of thousands
顯微鏡才能看見的嘴巴 稱為氣孔
of microscopic mouths called Stomata.
植物通過它們呼吸
Plants breathe through them,
吸入二氧化碳
taking in carbon dioxide
呼出我們賴以生存的氧氣
and exhaling the oxygen that we need to live.
地球上可以沒有我們
The plants can survive without us.
但是我們還有其他動物
But we and all the other animals...
離開它們就死翹翹了
we'd be toast without them.
地球通過陽光獲取食物
The plants make food out of sunlight.
我們動物做不到
We animals can't do that.
想看它們是怎麼做到的
To see how they do it,
我們還要潛的更深
we have to go deeper,
把我們變小大約1千倍
make ourselves about a thousand times smaller
才能進入它們的寶庫
to get into their treasure house,
它們把好東西都藏在裏面
the place where they keep the good stuff...
那就是葉綠素
the chlorophyll.
它雖然是個分子 可是卻能負責把陽光轉換成能量
That's the molecule that converts sunlight into energy.
每個長方形都是一個植物細胞
Every one of those rectangles is a plant cell.
還有那些小綠車 那都是它的能量工廠
And those tiny green vehicles are its energy factories.
如果我們可以竊取它們的商業機密
If we could steal their trade secrets,
又能帶來一次嶄新的工業革命
it would trigger a new industrial revolution.
但是要偷窺它們
But to spy on them,
我們還得潛得更深
we're gonna need to go deeper still.
想像之舟這次又要將我們帶去哪個截然不同的世界呢
What alien world has the ship of the imagination carried us to this time?
它是個宇宙
It's the cosmos...
在露珠裏面的宇宙
Contained within a dewdrop.
我們現在做的就是工業間諜活動
We're on an industrial espionage mission.
如果想刺探葉綠體的商業機密
If we can penetrate the trade secrets
葉綠體裏的製作過程
of the manufacturing process in that chloroplast,
就當我們的全部未來就靠它了
let's just say our whole future hangs in the balance.
葉綠體利用陽光將水分子
This chloroplast is using sunlight to break water molecules
分解成氫原子和氧原子
into atoms of hydrogen and oxygen.
將氫氣與二氧化碳結合產生糖
It combines the hydrogen with carbon dioxide to make sugar,
將氧氣作為廢氣排出
and releases the oxygen as a waste product.
要一探究竟 我們還要潛的更深
To see how it happens, we have to go even deeper,
變得更小
get even smaller.
小到原子級別
We're talking atomic scale.
成功了
Bingo.
這條流水線是分子工業基地的核心
This assembly line is the heartof the molecular industrial complex.
在分子這個級別
At the molecular level,
速度快到我們看不到
things happen too fast for us to see.
所以我們必須讓它們慢下來
So we'll have to slow them down
放慢十億倍
about a billion times.
那些大分子就是二氧化碳
Those larger molecules are carbon dioxide.
每一個分子
Each one of them is made
由1個碳原子和2個氧原子組成
of one carbon and two oxygen atoms.
當陽光照射葉綠素的分子
When sunlight strikes a green molecule of chlorophyll,
就會產生一系列的化學反應
it sets in motion a series of chemical reactions,
分解水分子
breaking apart water molecules
釋放活潑的電子
and freeing energetic electrons.
這只是日班的活
And that's just the day shift,
只在日光注入能量時工作
when sunlight supplies the incoming stream of energy.
還有一組不分晝夜的工作
There's a second shift that works day and night
利用預留的太陽能工作
using the solar energy kept in reserve.
自由電子的能量開始工作了
The energy of the free electrons is put to work,
將二氧化碳與水中的氫結合
combining carbon dioxide with hydrogen from the water.
產生糖  用以儲存太陽能
The end product is sugar,which stores the solar energy.
葉綠體從事太陽能採集工作
The chloroplast is a three-billion-year-old
長達30億年
solar energy collector.
微觀世界的太陽能電池
This sub-microscopic solar battery
驅動了所有的森林 田地
is what drives all the forests and the fields
甚至是海中的浮游生物
and the plankton of the seas.
還有動物
And the animals.
包括我們
Including us.
太陽能的生物圈
The solar-powered biosphere
比我們整個人類文明收集並處理的能量多出6倍
collects and processes six times more power than our entire civilization
我們瞭解化學層面的光合作用工作原理
We understand on a chemical level how photosynthesis works.
我們可以在實驗室複製這樣的過程
We can recreate the process in a laboratory.
但是我們做不到植物這麼好
But we're not as good at it as plants are.
這並不奇怪
And it's not surprising,
因為大自然已經這樣工作幾十億年了
considering nature has been at this for billions of years,
而我們才剛開始
and we've only just started.
如果我們可以知道
But if we could figure out
光合作用的商業機密
the trade secrets of photosynthesis,
如今我們賴以生存的其他形式的能量
every of other source of energy we depend on today...
煤 石油 天然氣都可以淘汰了
coal, oil, natural gas would become obsolete.
光合作用是終極綠色能源
Photosynthesis is the ultimate green power.
它不會污染大氣
It doesn't pollute the air
事實上 碳中和人造光合作用可以很大程度上
and is, in fact, carbon neutral. Artificial photosynthesis on a big enough scale
減少溫室效應
could reduce the greenhouse effect
所帶來的氣候變化
that's driving climate change in a dangerous direction.
這裏開始蒸發了
Uh-oh, place is evaporating.
該撤了
Time to get out of here.
露珠的生命一閃即逝
How fleeting is the life of a dewdrop.
它在寒冷的夜裏從稀薄的空氣中凝結而成
It condenses from thin air in the cool of the night,
卻在日出之後無影無蹤
only to vanish with the heat of the day.
它的居民怎麼辦 水熊蟲呢
And what of its inhabitants, the tardigrades?
它們不會有事的
They'll be fine.
因為它們可以幾年不喝水
They can go without water for years.
很難想像
It's hard to imagine,
覆蓋地球表面的植物
but plants covered the surface of the earth
幾億年後
for hundreds of millions of years
才開出第一朵花
before they put forth their first flower.
大約1億年前
That was about a hundred million years ago,
恐龍滅絕前不久
shortly before the dinosaurs were wiped out.
當時世界的顏色一定很單調
Our world must've been a relatively drab-looking place back then,
只有綠色和褐色
dominated by shades of green and brown.
是的那時是有大樹和蕨類 還有其他的植物
Yeah, there were giant trees and ferns and other plant life,
但是沒有紫色的鳶尾花
but not the purple of an iris
也沒有紅色的玫瑰花
or the crimson of a red, red rose.
蘭花是最早出現的花之一
Orchids were among the first flowering species
現在它們有著最多的品種
to appear on earth, and they're the most diverse.
達爾文特別癡迷馬達加斯加的彗星蘭
Darwin was particularly fascinated by the comet orchid of Madagascar,
這種花的花粉藏在一條又長又細的花徑底部
a flower whose pollen is hidden at the bottom of a very long, thin spur.
預測能力是驗證一種理論的最好方法
There can be no stronger test of an idea \than its predictive power.
根據他的物競天擇的進化論基礎
On the basis of his theory of evolution through natural selection
達爾文推測
Darwin speculated that somewhere
在馬達加斯加島上 一定有一種會飛的昆蟲
on the island of Madagascar, there must live flying insects
長著非常長的舌頭
with extraordinarily lengthy tongues,
長的足夠接觸到那些花粉
ones long enough to reach the pollen.
從沒人看過這種動物
No one had ever seen such a beast there,
但是達爾文堅信
but Darwin insisted
肯定有這樣的動物存在
that an animal fitting this description must exist.
當時相信他的人不多
Few people at the time believed him.
直到50多年後
It wasn't until more than 50 years later
才證明了達爾文的猜測是正確的
that Darwin was proven right.
1903年 有一種被稱為馬島長喙天蛾的蛾子在馬達加斯加被發現
In 1903, a huge hawk moth, called the Morgan's sphinx was discovered in Madagascar.
受到彗星蘭花粉香味的吸引
Attracted by the Comet Orchid's scent,
這蛾子用它1英尺長的口器吸食花粉
the moth slurps its pollen with its foot-long tongue,
和達爾文猜測的一樣
exactly as Darwin expected it would.
更令人驚奇的是 發現這種蛾子時
It's even more amazing that the Morgan's sphinx was discovered
馬達加斯加島上超過90%的雨林已經遭到破壞
when you consider that more than 90% of Madagascar's rain forest had been destroyed.
在達爾文著名的猜測多年後
In the years since Darwin's famous prediction,
這種蛾子很有可能已經滅絕
this moth species could have easily become extinct
就和其他同類一樣
with all the others...
它們每一個都是生命詩篇中的獨特樂章
every one of them a unique phrase of life's poetry,
由萬古的進化寫在原子中
written in the atoms by eons of evolution.
丁香花的芬芳
Ah, the fragrance of lilacs.
這種香味
It's one of those scents
讓人不禁浮想翩翩
that triggers a whole constellation of associations,
很久前的每個夏天都是如此
all those junes of long ago.
怎會如此
But how does that happen?
味道是怎麼會讓你的頭腦中出現影像的
How does a smell prompt a movie to start running in your head?
那不是我們能看到的
It's not something we can see.
有可能是象光一樣的能量波嗎
Could it be a wave of energy, like light?
還是一種微觀粒子呢
Or is it some kind of microscopic particle?
其實它是一種分子
It's actually a molecule.
每種味道 不論是來自烤焦的麵包
Every odor we can sense, whether it comes from burnt toast
還是汽油 或者一片丁香花
gasoline, or a field of lilacs,
都是一大片的分子
is a cloud of molecules.
這些分子有種特定的形狀
These molecules have particular shapes.
當我吸入它們時
When I inhale them,
它們刺激我鼻子中一組特定的感受細胞
they stimulate a particular set of receptor cells in my nose.
一種電子信號傳遞到我的大腦
An electrical signal then travels to my brain,
告訴我這個味道是丁香花的香味
which identifies the scent as lilac.
不同的分子攜帶不同的味道
Other scents are carried by different molecules
它們的形狀也各異
with different shapes.
但當我聞到一朵花 或者篝火
But when I smell a flower or the smoke from a campfire
或者機器的潤滑油
or the grease from a motor gear,
通常是涌現出大量的記憶
I'm often flooded with memories.
為什麼花香這麼簡單的東西能夠引起強烈的記憶呢
Why is it that a simple thing such as the scent of a flower can trigger powerful memories?
一定和我們的大腦進化方式有關
It has to do with the way our brains have evolved.
當大腦中的嗅神經受到刺激
Our sense of smell kicks in
我們的嗅覺開始工作
when the olfactory nerve in our brain is stimulated.
這種神經就在扁桃體旁邊
That nerve is located very close to the amygdala,
是我們情感體驗的組成部分
a structure that is integral to our experience of emotion.
也很靠近海馬體
It's also very close to the Hippocampus,
產生記憶的地方
which helps us form memories.
神經網絡將氣味信號
The network of neurons that carry the scent signal
從我的鼻子傳遞到
from my nose to my brain has been fine-tuned
我這經過上億年進化的大腦
over hundreds of millions of years of evolution.
這是一種生存機制 給我們發出警告
It's a survival mechanism that can alert us
讓我們避開危險
to danger or guide us to safety.
如果你能提前發覺獵食者
If you you can detect the predator
在他發動攻擊前
before he's near enough to strike,
或者在被大火困在森林前
or the fire before it traps you in the forest,
就會大大增加你的生存幾率
you have a much better chance to survive
然後把你的基因傳給下一代
and pass on your genes to the next generation.
花田里的迷人芬芳
That lovely scent from this field of flowers
發出一組獨特的神經信號密碼
sets off a unique combination of nerve signals.
只有這個密碼可以打開我們大腦中
Only that exact combination can crack the safe
儲存關於丁香花的記憶保險箱
where the memory of lilacs is stored inside my brain.
啥味道
Wonder who they're for.
我們或許以後會知道
Maybe we'll find out later.
但還有一個隱藏著的宇宙在等著我們
But first, there's another hidden cosmos waiting for us.
植物們靜靜的呼吸
The plants are softly breathing,
吸入二氧化碳分子
inhaling molecules of carbon dioxide
呼出氧氣分子
and exhaling molecules of oxygen.
和我相反
And I'm doing the opposite.
與雪花和指紋不一樣
Unlike snowflakes and fingerprints,
同類的原子或分子
atoms or molecules of the same kind
都是完全的相同
are utterly identical to one another.
每次吸氣
With every breath we take,
我們吸入的分子數量
we inhale as many molecules as there are stars
和已知宇宙的所有星星數量一樣多
in all the galaxies in the visible universe.
呼出的氣體與空氣流通交換
And every breath we exhale is circulated through the air,
在大地上逐漸混合
and mixed gradually across the continents,
讓別人也可以呼吸
it becomes available for others to breathe.
一起呼吸
Breathe with me.
我們大致吸入了1億的分子
We all just inhaled about 100 million molecules
這些分子曾經被所有的前人
that once passed through the lungs of everyone
呼吸過
who ever lived before us.
想想看 這種原子的再生
Think of it... This kind of atomic reincarnation
將我們與遠古的祖先聯繫在一起
is another link to our distant ancestors,
包括那些最初帶領我們探索
including those who first launched us on our explorations
未知宇宙的人
of the unseen universes.
這些宇宙就如同你我一樣真實
These universes are as real as you or me,
就在我們的身邊
and they surround us.
曾經我們如夢初醒
There was a moment when we awakened
開始用嶄新的方法審視和思考
to a new way of thinking and seeing.
那是大約2500年前
It happened about 2,500 years ago
在希臘的小島上
on the Greek islands that lie
位於東方與西方文明之間
between the empires of the east and west.
商人 遊客 水手們自由的融合
There, merchants, tourists and sailors freely mingled,
交流各自關於偉人和神的傳說
exchanging tales of great kings and gods.
在愛奧尼亞有個叫米利都的城市 就是今天的土耳其
In Ionian cities and towns like Miletus, in what is now Turkey,
一些現代生活的最基本元素
the most fundamental elements
在那裏出現了
of the way we live now first appeared.
第一次對生活形式的重現
Here, for the first time, reenactments of aspects of life
由專業人士創作並演繹
created and executed by professionals
期待可以深深感動觀眾的內心
with the expectation of touching something deep within the hearts of the audience,
或者只是逗他們開心
or just making them laugh...
誕生了第一場演出 戲劇還有喜劇
The first plays, dramas and comedies, were performed.
還有一種極其嶄新的概念
Here, also, was born a radical new idea:
民治政府
Government by the people.
從最初模糊的不完美的概念 到如今的民主
The first inklings, imperfect then as now, of a democracy,
普通民眾也可以擁有某些權力的觀念
and the notion that the ordinary citizen might possess certain rights
在那時 在這裏誕生萌芽
come to us from this time and place.
但在我看來 這個古代世界帶給我們的
But in my view, the most revolutionary innovation of all
最革命性的創新觀念是
to come to us from this ancient world was the idea
自然事件並不是眾神給我們的懲罰或獎勵
that natural events were neither punishment nor reward from capricious gods.
大自然的規律不一定要用
The workings of nature could be explained
超自然力量來解釋
without invoking the supernatural.
表達出這種觀念的第一人
The first person to express this thought
名叫 泰利斯
was a man named Thales.
希臘哲學家
當閃電或地震時
When the thunder clapped or the earth quaked,
並不是因為我們的所作所為觸怒了嚴厲的眾神
it was not because something you did had somehow displeased the very demanding gods.
只是一種我們可以理解的自然過程的結果
No, it was the result of natural processes that we were capable of understanding.
儘管沒有任何記錄他原話的書籍留存下來
Though none of the books he is said to have written survive,
泰利斯的思想光芒依然照耀我們
Thales kindled a flame that still burns to this day:
宇宙運行的井井有條的原因
The very idea of cosmos out of chaos,
宇宙由我們可以理解的自然法則控制的這種觀念
a universe governed by the order of natural laws that we can actually figure out.
這種偉大的觀念在泰利斯的頭腦中萌芽
This is the epic adventure that began in the mind of Thales.
僅僅在泰利斯身後100年
Only a century following Thales' death,
又一個天才出現了
another genius came along.
他與眾不同的是
And he, more than any other,
第一個發現了
was the first to discover the existence
我們周圍未知宇宙的存在
of the hidden universes that surround us.
來自阿夫季拉的德謨克利特是為真正的科學家
Democritus of Abdera was a true scientist,
充滿探索宇宙激情的男人
a man with a passionate desire to know the cosmos
也很會享受
and to have fun.
他曾說 "沒有狂歡的生活
This is the man who once said, "a life without parties
...就像沒有盡頭的漫漫長路"
would be like an endless road without an end."
這就樣嗎
You mean, that's it?
就這麼簡單嗎
That's all there is?
只是虛無中的一堆原子
Just a bunch of atoms in a void?
然也
Yep.
你想想看
Well, think about it.
這個世界必然是
The world has to be made
由虛無中無數的不可見的微粒組成
of countless indivisible particles in a void.
否則萬物就不會移動 生長 被分離或改變
Otherwise, nothing could move or grow, be divided or changed.
如果沒有原子和容納它們的空曠太空的話
Without atoms and empty space for them to move in,
這個世界會變得像鐵板一塊 死氣沉沉
the world would be solid, static and dead.
別傷心了 少年
so don't be sad, my friends.
想想那無盡的可能性吧
Just think of the infinite possibilities
由那些原子排列組合所帶來的可能性
that arise from different arrangements of those atoms.
向這杯的酒 還有酒中的原子們致敬
Here's to the atoms in this cup and in this wine...
還有它們帶來的歡樂
And to the laughter they make possible.
當時的酒杯都由泥土燒製而成
遍佈酒杯的泥土
Dispersed through the Clay of the cup
都是用顯微鏡才能看到的礦物微粒
are microscopic mineral grains,
晶體的一種
different kinds of crystals,
每個都有與眾不同的原子結構
each with its own distinctive atomic architecture.
礦物結構很精妙
Mineral structures are exquisite,
但是它們的結構形式有限
but they have a limited repertoire.
一粒石英就是一個由3個相同原子組成的晶格集合體
A grain of quartz is a lattice of the same three atoms
沒有變化 不斷重複
repeated, without variation, over and over again.
即使是相對複雜的礦物晶格 比如黃寶石
Even a relatively complex mineral lattice like topaz,
由10個左右的原子組成
composed of ten or so atoms,
也只是相同的原子結構
can only repeat the identical atomic structure
不斷重複
again and again.
為了轉換到另一個維度
為了將它從不斷重複的晶格束縛中釋放
to free it from the lattice prison of endless repetition,
你需要一個可以從任何方向與其他原子相結合的原子
you need an atom that can bond in all directions with other atoms like itself
它也要能與其他不同的原子相結合
as well as with atoms of different kinds.
看 碳原子
Behold the carbon atom...
地球上生命不可缺少的元素
the essential element for life on earth.
為什麼
Why?
碳之所以特殊 是因為它可以一次與最多4種原子結合
Carbon is special because it can bond with up to four other atoms at a time.
它可以與許多其他種類的原子結合
It can connect with many different kinds of atoms,
也包括其他碳原子
as well as other carbon atoms.
它可以彎曲成環狀
It can curl into rings
也可以連成一條線
and string together into chains,
組成遠比任何一種晶體都複雜的分子
building molecules far more complex than any crystal.
其它原子都沒有這種靈活性
No other atom has the same flexibility.
就算擁有類似化學屬性的原子也不行
Even atoms that have similar chemical properties,
比如 硅
like silicon,
也無法像碳這樣組成豐富多樣的分子
can't form the amazing variety of molecules built on carbon.
這種碳基分子 我們稱為 蛋白質
The carbon-based molecules we call proteins,
組成生命的分子
the molecules of life,
包含了成千上萬的原子
contain literally hundreds of thousands of atoms.
碳原子是世界上一切生物分子的支柱
Carbon atoms are the backbone of the molecules that make every living thing on earth,
包括我們
including us.
這就是岩石和生物的區別
That's the difference between rocks and living things.
生命可以製造出大量的
Life can make enormous molecules
有著驚人體積和複雜性的分子
of stunning size and complexity,
自由自在地隨機應變
freeing matter to improvise,
進化
evolve,
甚至 愛
and even love.
孩子的父親 您別擔心
Take it easy, dad.
他並沒有真的碰到的她
He never actually touched her.
日常生活中以原子這個層面上來說
In everyday life on our world, on the scale of atoms,
物體絕對不會相互接觸到對方
material objects never really touch.
每個原子的中心都有一個原子核
Each atom has a tiny nucleus at its center,
被力線電子雲所包圍
surrounded by an electron cloud of lines of force.
當原子彼此接近時
As the atoms approach each other,
男孩的電子雲
the boy's electron clouds
推開女孩的電子雲
push away the girl's.
超過99.9%的原子物質都集中在它的原子核中
More than 99.9% of the matter of any atom is concentrated in its nucleus.
原子核被電子雲包圍
The nucleus is surrounded by an electron cloud
電子雲形成無形的力場
which produces an invisible field of force,
就像減震器
and acts like a shock absorber.
電子雲的結構決定了元素的本質
The configuration of the electron cloud determines the nature of an element.
以地球上物質的正常情況來說
In the ordinary course of things here on earth,
原子核永遠不會彼此接觸
the nuclei never touch.
我們有接觸的感覺
We have a sensation of touching,
那只不過是看不見的力場
but that's really just our invisible force fields
相互重疊的同時相互排斥
overlapping and repelling each other.
相較於原子的其他部分 原子核非常小
The nucleus is very small compared to the rest of the atom.
如果原子像這個教堂這麼大
If an atom were the size of this cathedral,
原子核的尺寸也就是那粒灰塵的大小
its nucleus would be the size of that mote of dust.
原子的大部分是空曠的空間
An atom is mostly empty space.
為了理解事物的本質
To understand the nature of matter,
我們要去更深的地方
we have to go deeper still,
去一個比原子還小10萬倍的地方
to a place 100,000 times smaller than the atom:
那就是它的原子核
Its nucleus.
宇宙中最簡單 但又最豐富的原子是氫原子
The simplest and most plentiful atom in the cosmos is hydrogen.
它的原子核只有一個質子
Its nucleus is a single proton,
所以它在元素週期表中位於第一位
which makes hydrogen element number one.
圍繞著它的雲
The clouds that surround it
是它唯一的電子可以運行的範圍
are the realms where the atom's lone electron is permitted to roam.
原子核有兩個質子時會是什麼情況
What happens when you have a nucleus with two protons?
質子相互排斥
Protons repel each other.
為了讓它們保持在原子核內
In order to hold them together in a nucleus,
你還需要另一種粒子 稱之 中子
you need other particles called neutrons.
它們的工作是防止質子出軌
Their job is to keep the protons from getting out of line.
它們用強大的核引力壓制質子
They overwhelm the protons
原子核有2個質子的元素排名第2
A nucleus with two protons is element number two,
名曰 氦
otherwise known as helium.
原子核有6個質子的元素排名第6
A nucleus with six protons is element number six,
就是碳
which is carbon,
生命的基石
the fundamental building block of life.
金元素的原子核有79個質子
The nucleus of a gold atom has 79 protons.
在周圍的雲中 它們吸引了79個電子
They attract 79 electrons in clouds around it
光與這些電子的互動
The way light interacts with those electrons
就是黃金閃光的原因
is what makes gold glitter.
原子核中每增加一個質子
Every additional proton in the nucleus
都需要有足夠的中子把它們聚集在一起
requires enough neutrons to bind them together...
在一定程度上
Up to a point.
你能塞進原子核的中子數量是有上限的
There's an upper limit to the number of neutrons you can stuff into a nucleus
否則會變得不穩定
before it becomes unstable.
有個地方
I know a place
不同原子的原子核
where the nuclei of different atoms
能夠相互接觸
actually do touch each other.
太陽看上去像個實體
The sun looks like a solid object,
但並不是這樣的
but it's not.
它把所有的原子都加熱到了氣態
It's so hot that all its atoms are always in their gaseous state.
地球上將原子束縛產生液態和固體的粘合力
The bonds that join atoms to make solids and liquids on earth
不足以承受熾熱太陽的熱量
are not strong enough to withstand the heat of the broiling sun
那些耀眼氣體的弧形氣流使地球看上去渺小
Those arcing streams of incandescent gas that dwarf the earth
其實它們都受到太陽表面之下發射出來的力場的磁力線引導
are guided by magnetic lines of force that emanate from below the surface of the sun.
太陽怎麼會這麼熱
Why is the sun so hot?
因為它驚人的引力
Because its own stupendous gravity
將原子們積壓在一起
is squeezing its atoms together.
引力的能量轉換成
The energy of gravity is being transformed
移動原子的能量
into the energy of moving atoms.
那就是熱的來源
That's what heat is.
越到太陽的內部
The deeper we go into the sun,
擠壓的力量越大
the greater the squeezing
溫度也越高
and the higher the temperature.
在太陽的中心
In the heart of the sun,
原子的移動速度快到 它們碰撞時發生融化 原子核發生接觸
the atoms are moving so fast that when they collide, they fuse. Their nuclei touch.
太陽就是核聚變反應堆
The sun is a nuclear fusion reactor,
由它的引力來維繫
held together by its own gravity.
它在向內拉的引力和向外推的熱浪間取得平衡
It's balanced between the inward pull of gravity and the outward push of its hot gases.
這種平衡持續幾十億年
That balance has lasted billions of years,
提供了使地球上生物進化成為可能的穩定性
providing stability that made possible the evolution of life on earth.
在太陽的核心 氫融合後變成氦
In the sun's core, the fusion of hydrogen into helium
以光子的形式釋放核能
releases nuclear energy in the form of photons.
這些光的微粒
These particles of light
慢慢的來到表面
slowly work their way to the surface,
就是我們所見的日光
where they're seen as sunlight.
氦原子就是太陽核反應的殘渣
Helium is the ash of the sun's nuclear furnace.
太陽是一顆中等尺寸的恆星
The sun is a medium-sized star.
它的核心溫度只不過1千萬度
Its core is only a lukewarm ten million degrees...
只夠融化氫原子
hot enough to fuse hydrogen,
卻不足以融化氦原子
but too cold to fuse helium.
銀河系中有很多恆星
There are many stars in the galaxy
比太陽熱得多
that get much hotter,
因為它們質量更大
because they're more massive
引力更大
and have more gravity.
這些恆星將氦融化成更重的元素 比如 碳和氧
Such stars fuse helium into heavier elements, like carbon and oxygen.
等它們老了
In their old age,
它們慢慢的將這些元素散播到太空中
they gently diffuse these elements into space.
還有些恆星 質量更大
Other stars, more massive yet,
一生苦短 英年早逝
live fast and die young
卒於災難性的超新星大爆炸
in cataclysmic supernova explosions.
我們的銀河系中 每一百年 這樣的恆星就會變成超新星
In our galaxy, such stars go supernova about once a century.
這些爆炸比太陽核心熱的多得多
Those explosions are far hotter than the core of the sun
熱的足夠把鐵元素變成更重的元素
hot enough to transform elements like iron into all the heavier ones
並把它們噴向太空
and spew them into space.
大麥哲倫星雲
The large magellanic cloud
使我們銀河系的鄰居
is a neighboring galaxy of our milky way.
可以在南半球的星空中看到
It's visible in the skies of the Southern hemisphere.
當超新星爆炸時
When a supernova explodes,
它的亮度超過它的整個星系
its brightness rivals that of its entire galaxy.
但這些光也只是爆炸產生的能量中的大約1%
But all that light is only about one percent of the energy liberated in the explosion.
其它的能量化成宇宙中最常見
The rest of the energy is carried off by the most common
也最神秘的微粒
and the most mysterious particles in the cosmos.
現在就有幾萬億的這種微粒穿過你的身體
There are trillions of them passing through you right now,
然而即使為了找到一個這樣的微粒
and yet tracking down even one of them
也需要我們去到地球上最離奇的地方
will take us to one of the strangest places on earth.
追蹤野生的中微子
Stalking the wild neutrino
是最小眾的運動
is the rarest of sport.
追蹤它們的難度 難得令人驚訝
The lengths one must go to track them down is nothing short of astonishing
歡迎來到超級神岡探測器
Welcome to Super Kamiokande,
日本地下中微子探測器的內部
the subterranean Japanese neutrino detection chamber.
我們身處地表之下超過半英里
We're more than a half mile beneath earth's surface.
也就是大約1公里
你或許會問 哪個正常人
You might ask, "well, who in their right mind
會把天文台埋在這麼深的地下
would bury an astronomical observatory so far underground?"
這些人狩獵宇宙中最神出鬼沒的獵物
Those who hunt the most elusive prey in the cosmos:
中微子
The neutrino.
這個龐大的光探測器陣列
This enormous array of light detectors
圍繞著5萬噸蒸餾水
surrounding 50,000 tons of distilled water
設計這個陷阱只為了抓捕中微子
is a trap designed to catch neutrinos only.
其他粒子 例如宇宙射線
Other particles, such as cosmic rays...
大部分是從太空中落下的質子和電子
mostly protons and electrons that rain down from space...
無法穿過我們頭頂的岩石
cannot get through all that rock above us.
但這些對中微子來說都不是障礙
But matter poses no obstacle to a neutrino.
中微子可以穿過100光年厚的鐵板
A neutrino could pass through 100 light-years of steel
甚至不會減速
without even slowing down.
中微子幾乎不受其他物質影響
Neutrinos hardly interact with matter at all
這就是為什麼我們需要如此大費周章
That's why you need so much of it to catch even one of them.
在很罕見的情況下
On those rare occasions when a neutrino
中微子和其他微粒發生衝突
actually does collide with a particle of ordinary matter,
它會產生一個幽靈般的環形閃光
it produces a ghostly, ring-shaped flash of light.
我們守株待兔
We're lying in wait
等一個幾乎沒有重量的微粒
for a particle that weighs next to nothing.
甚至比電子
Even the miniscule electron
還輕100萬倍
has more than a million times its mass...
那裏
There!
1987年 當大麥哲倫星雲的超新星爆炸時
When the supernova in the large magellanic cloud blew its top in 1987
這就是當時這裏出現的景象
this is what it would have looked like in here.
請記住 大麥哲倫星雲
Now remember, the large magellanic cloud
在我們的南半球
is in our Southern hemisphere,
所以這些中微子不是穿過
so the neutrinos didn't come through
我們頭頂上半英里的岩石
that half-mile of rock above us,
而是必須穿過我們身下
they had to pass through the thousands of miles
幾千英里的岩石和鐵才能到達這裏
of rock and iron below us to reach this detector.
但是最酷的事情是
But the coolest thing was that those neutrinos
中微子比超新星發出的光早3小時到達地球
hit earth three hours before the light from the supernova did.
如果沒有什麼能比光跑得快
If nothing can travel faster than light,
這又是怎麼回事呢
how could that possibly be?
星之將死
This is a dead star walking.
看上去好像挺正常 但是在它的深處大災難已經發生
It may look normal, but deep within it something cataclysmic is happening
這顆藍色的超級巨大的恆星
This blue super giant star
內部即將發生爆炸
has already begun to explode inside.
如同即將沉船上的老鼠 慌不擇路
Like rats deserting a sinking ship, the neutrinos
即將爆炸的恆星內部產生的中微子
produced in the heart of the exploding star
以接近光速的速度向外逃逸
race outward at near the speed of light,
幾秒內穿過覆蓋物
through overlying mass in only a few seconds
但是爆炸氣體的衝擊波
But the shock wave of the exploding gas
從恆星內部緩緩踱出
plods along from the center of the star
只有光速的萬分之一
at 1/10,000 the speed of light
直到最後抵達
until it finally reaches
恆星的表面
the star's surface,
變成了1987年的超新星
turning it into supernova 1987a.
要好幾個小時
It took hours for the explosion
爆炸才能到達表面 然後向外噴發
to reach the surface of the star and blow it wide open,
將極度炙熱的內核炸開
exposing the super hot core.
中微子已經贏在了起跑線上
The neutrinos had an insurmountable head start.
這就是為什麼閃光會比中微子晚這麼多到達地球
That's why the flash of light arrived on earth so much later than the shower of neutrinos.
在「野生」中微子被捕獲前
Before anyone had ever snared the wild neutrino,
它已經存在於理論物理學家的腦海中
it existed in the mind of a theoretical physicist.
就如同查爾斯·達爾文知道
Just as Charles Darwin knew
必定有一種超級長鼻生物生活在馬達加斯加
there must be an extremely long-nosed creature flying around somewhere in Madagascar
一位名叫沃爾夫岡·泡利的20世紀物理學家
a 20th-century physicist named Wolfgang Pauli...
致力於尋找一種微粒
was desperately seeking a particle
用來拯救現代物理學的支柱之一
to rescue one of the pillars of modern physics,
能量守恆定律
the law of the conservation of energy.
我為什麼沒有退縮
So why didn't I flinch?
因為科學定律與其它人類活動的根本區別
Because the laws of science differ fundamentally from those of other human endeavors
要將一種設想變成科學定律
In order for an idea to become a scientific law,
必須要無懈可擊
it has to unbreakable.
這就是為何我願意賭上我的臉
That's why I was willing to bet this face
來證明能量守恆定律
on the laws of conservation of energy.
如果你在家自己嘗試
Now, if you try this at home,
千萬小心不要推這個球
take care not to give the cannonball a push.
那會增加能量
That's adding energy,
這球肯定會回來造成傷害
and the ball will surely come back and do some damage.
只要像這樣輕輕放手
You just have to let it go, like this.
抬起這個球
By lifting the ball,
你給它勢能
you give it gravitational energy,
使它可能墜落並且加速
which is the potential to fall and accelerate.
球在弧度底部時速度達到最大
The cannonball is going fastest when it's at the bottom of its arc
在那個時候
and at that moment,
它把所有的勢能轉化成動能
it's converted all of its gravitational energy to the energy of motion.
搖擺時 球不斷轉換能量
As it swings, the cannonball is constantly exchanging
從一種轉換到另一種
one of these two kinds of energy for the other,
但是能量的總量保持不變
but the total amount of energy remains constant.
這就是能量守恆定律的例子
That's an example of the law of conservation of energy.
放開球的那刻
Once the cannonball is released,
它就無法獲得更多的能量
it can never gain more energy than it had to begin with.
它不可能飛過來打到我的鼻子
It has no way to fly up and break my nose.
能量這筆賬永遠是平衡的
The energy accounting books are always strictly balanced.
做不得假
There's no such thing as cheating.
在20世紀
So in the 20th century,
當科學家首次精確測量出原子的能量
when physicists first calculated the energy of atoms precisely,
他們驚訝的發現了
they were startled to discover
違背這個定律的情況
an apparent violation of this law.
他們發現在一些放射性原子中
They found that in some radioactive atoms,
原子核自發的噴出一個電子
the nucleus can spontaneously eject an electron.
將原子轉變成另一種元素
This transforms the atom into a different element.
物理學家迷惑了
The physicists were mystified.
逃逸電子的能量
The energy of the escaped electron
加上新元素的能量
plus that of the new element
少於原有原子核的能量
adds up to less than the energy in the original nucleus.
定律指出
But the law says,
能量既不會憑空產生 也不會憑空消失
"thou shall not destroy or create energy."
那麼那些能量去了哪裏
So where did the missing energy go?
1930年
In 1930...
沃爾夫岡·泡利預測
Wolfgang Pauli predicted
一定有一種未知的微粒
there must be an undiscovered particle,
帶走了這些能量
one that makes off with the missing energy.
當時 沃爾夫岡·泡利感嘆
At the time, Pauli lamented
如此微小的虛幻微粒
that such a phantom particle might be so minute,
迅速而難以琢磨
swift and evasive
可能永遠都探測不到了
as to forever defy detection.
好在那只是他罕有的一次錯誤預測
But that was a rare failure of his imagination
因為科學家總是不斷
because science is always searching
尋找探索的新方法
for a way to go deeper still.
幾十年後
A generation later,
在核反應堆的輻射中
Pauli's neutrinos were actually detected for the first time
中微子第一次被人們探測到
in radiation from a nuclear reactor.
雖然很艱難 但從那之後我們不斷找到更多的
And we've been finding them, with difficulty, ever since.
如今 有些科學家們
There are scientists today
嘗試利用那些中微子
who are trying to find a way to ride those neutrinos
來研究時間的起源
all the way back to the beginning of time.
一起去看看他們的成就  那是一面永恆之牆
We'll go as far as they have gone to come up against the wall of forever.
永恆之牆並不新鮮
The wall of forever is nothing new.
我們的祖先也遇到過
Our ancestors came up against it
幾乎就在他們第一次開始想像時
almost as soon as they first started imagining it.
幾千年前 公元前13世紀
A million dawns ago, in the 13th century bc,
埃及人建造了阿布辛貝勒神廟
the Egyptian built this temple at Abu Simbel
紀念法老王拉美西斯二世
to honor the Pharaoh Ramses II,
在這裏留下了四座巨大的石像
depicted here in four colossal statues.
在這位偉大君主之上真正的王者其實是鷹首太陽神
Reigning even above even this mighty king is the falcon-headed Ra-Harakhti
太陽之神
God of the sun.
這座神廟被設計成每年只有兩次
The temple was designed so that the light from the rising sun
旭日的霞光金輝才會射入神殿
could only enter the sanctuary on two days every year.
當光線照進神廟
As the rays enter the temple,
在貫穿整個神殿前
they burnish the statues of the gods with their golden light
日光使眾神的石像閃耀著金色的光芒
before penetrating the sanctuary.
但是 仍有一位神的石像依然處在陰影中
Even then, one God remains in shadow.
普塔 創造之神
Ptah, lord of creation,
彷彿暗示宇宙的起源注定永遠神秘
as if the origin of the universe must forever be concealed.
感受陽光照在臉上
Feel the sun on your face.
使你溫暖的能量
The energy that warms you
來自幾千萬年前
began its journey some ten million years ago
太陽的核心
in the heart of the sun.
與中微子不同
Unlike neutrinos,
質子需要
the photons needed
這麼久的時間才能從核心到達表面
that long to work their way out from the core to the surface.
為什麼
Why?
因為它們與太陽的原子每秒發生幾十億次的碰撞
Because they were colliding billions of times per second with the sun's atoms
每次撞擊都將它們推向不同的方向
every collision sending them off in a random direction.
它們一旦到達表面
But once they finally reached the surface,
它們就徹底解放 以光的速度
they were free to dash nonstop, at the speed of light
只用區區8分20秒 就來到你的面前
in a mere eight minutes and 20 seconds from the sun to you
一千萬歲高齡的陽光
Ten-million-year-old light on your face.
當那光離開太陽核心時 又是怎麼的景象呢
What was happening when that light left the heart of the sun?
宇宙年歷將宇宙
The cosmic calendar compresses
整整138億年的歷史
the entire 13.8 billion year history
壓縮到一年的時間內
of the universe into a single year.
每個月代表10億年
Every month represents about a billion years.
一天就是4千萬年
Every day, about 40 million years.
宇宙的歷史如此悠久 在年歷上
The universe is so old that, on the cosmic calendar,
1千萬年前 也只不過是
ten million years ago only takes us back as far as...
這一年的最後一天的下午6點
6:00 P.M. on the last evening of the last day of the year
那我們呢
And what about us?
人類還沒開始進化
Humans had yet to evolve.
1千萬年前
Ten million years ago,
我們的祖先還是類人猿
our ancestors were anthropoid apes,
活躍在非洲的叢林中
swinging through the trees of Africa.
對我們來說 1千萬年好像很久遠
To us, ten million years seems like a long time,
但是對於宇宙來說
but it's only the length of an afternoon
那只不過是半天而已
on the timescale of the cosmos.
45億年前 太陽開始放出光芒
The sun began fusing hydrogen 4,500 million years ago...
宇宙歷上的8月31號
August 31 on the cosmic calendar.
我們的銀河系
Our milky way galaxy
大約100億歲
is about 10,000 million years old.
第一個星系比它還早幾十億年
The first galaxies formed about a few billion years earlier.
有東西阻擋我們回到更遠的過去
Something keeps me from going any further back in time.
是什麼呢
What is this?
是光與時間的本質
It's the nature of light and time.
因為光的速度有限
Because light travels at a finite speed,
我們所看到的宇宙 其實只是過去的光
to look across space is to look back in time.
看得越遠
So the farther we see,
看到的光越古老
the older the light.
這是我們所能看到宇宙歷史上最古老的光
This is as far back in the history of the cosmos as we can see with light.
這是宇宙剛誕生的樣子
It's a baby picture of universe,
只有38萬歲
when it was only 380,000 years old.
宇宙歷上最初的15分鐘
That's 15 minutes into January 1 on the cosmic calendar
我們用微波望遠鏡看向宇宙的盡頭
If we look as far as we can see in any direction using microwave telescopes
看到的就是這樣
this is what we see,
大爆炸留下的光暈
the glow left over from the Big Bang.
想像一下 可觀測宇宙的所有物質和能量
Imagine that all the matter and energy of the observable universe
都被濃縮成這樣的大小
was concentrated into something no larger than this
這就是當時宇宙的大小
That's the size of the universe
當它只有一分之一萬億歲時
when it was a trillionth of a trillionth of a trillionth of a second old
幾千億個星系的物質與能量
All the matter and energy of the hundred billion galaxies
如今擴展到方圓幾十億光年的範圍
now splayed out across the billions of light-years
曾經都被禁錮在這個彈珠大小的東西內
were once pent up in something the size of a marble
你能想像出那顆彈珠有多緊密嗎
Can you imagine how tightly packed that marble must have been?
稠密得使任何光都無法穿過
Far too dense for any kind of light to move through it,
但這阻礙不了中微子
but no obstacle for the likes of neutrinos.
大爆炸必定產生了數量驚人的中微子
The big bang must have produced stupendous numbers of neutrinos,
它們順暢地穿過那些緊密得難以置信的物質
which flew unhindered through that inconceivable crush of matter
使它們幾乎無法被探測的最關鍵因素是
The very thing that makes them almost impossible to detect
它們可以穿過遮掩時間起源的厚重幕布
is what allows neutrinos to sail through the curtain that conceals the beginning of time
它們在哪裏
Where are they now?
在這裏 在那裏
They are here, they're there,
宇宙中無處不在
everywhere throughout the universe.
宇宙誕生時中微子就在你的內心深處
Neutrinos from creation are within you.
從一個彈珠
From a marble...
到整個宇宙
To the cosmos.
這是一條泰利斯和德謨克利特2500年前帶我們走上的路
This is the road that Thales and Democritus put us on some 2,500 years ago...
無盡的探索之路
a road of endless searching,
不斷的有條不紊的探索新的世界
a relentless, systematic hunt for new worlds
並且不斷加深對自然的理解
and an ever-deepening understanding of nature.
你們中有人會接過火炬 帶領我們走上一條更寬廣的大路嗎
Who among you will pick up that torch and take us down that next stretch of road?
中文翻譯： @SaltyEggPain timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息